We humans are becoming an urban species,
أصبحنا نحن البشر مخلوقات متحضرة،
so cities, they are our natural habitat.
والمدن موطننا الطبيعي.
That is where we live.
هذا هو المكان الذى نعيش فيه.
In 2014, over 54 percent
فى عام 2014، أكثر من 54%
of the world population
من سكان العالم
was living in cities,
كانوا يعيشون في المدن،
and I can bet you
وأستطيعُ أن أراهنكم
that so many of these people have thought
أن الكثير من هؤلاء البشر قد فكروا
of how they would do things differently,
في كيفية لو قاموا بعمل الأشياء بطرق مختلفة،
like if I only had the tools
مثل ماذا لو كان لدي الأدوات فقط
to change things in my city,
لتغيير الأشياء في مدينتي،
what would I do?
ماذا يمكنني أن أفعل؟
What would my dream city be like?
كيف ستبدو مدينة أحلامي؟
And these tools,
وهذه الأدوات،
this is just what we gave them.
هذه هي ما منحناهم فقط.
Two years ago, my team and I,
قبل عامين، أنا وفريقي،
we released a game,
أصدرنا لعبة،
"Cities: Skylines."
سيتيز: سكاي لاينز
It is a game about building cities.
إنها لعبة عن كيفية بناء المدن.
So I have always been interested in cities as systems.
كنتُ دومًا مهتمة بالمدن كنظم.
It's something that I find immensely interesting.
إنها شيء أجده مثيرًا للاهتمام كثيرًا.
But what I didn't understand
ولكن الشيء الذى لم أدركه
was that I am not alone in this.
كان بأنني لستُ الوحيدة في هذا.
People love cities.
يحب الناس المدن.
They are interested. They have ideas.
فهم مهتمون، ولديهم أفكار.
The game was an instant hit.
حققت اللعبة نجاحًا فوريًا.
So far, over three and a half million people have played it.
حتى الآن، لعب أكثر من 3.5 مليون شخص هذه اللعبة.
And it's not just about playing.
وهي ليست فقط حول اللعب.
We also have really awesome sharing systems.
لدينا أيضًا نظم مشاركة رائعة حقًا.
So people play, they create cities
يلعبُ الناس، ويبنون المدن
and then they are sharing these creations,
ومن ثم يشاركون مبتكراتهم،
showing off what they have made.
متفاخرين بما صنعوا.
And what I will show you
والذي سأعرضه لكم
is some of these cities
هو بعضًا من هذه المدن
created by the players.
بُنيت من قبل اللاعبين.
So the game is about self-expression,
تعبرُ اللعبة عن الذات،
creativity,
والإبداع،
not just overcoming the challenges posed by the simulation.
وليس فقط التغلب على التحديات التي تفرضها المحاكاة.
It is about showing what your cities look like.
إنها حول إظهار ما ستبدو عليه مدنكم.
So I have a couple of videos.
لديّ مقطعان من الفيديوهات،
These are from YouTube.
من اليوتيوب.
And these are some of the most interesting city designs I have seen.
وهذه من أكثر تصاميم المدن إثارةً التي شاهدتها.
So they are all different,
فجميعها مختلف،
and I hope you like all of these.
وأتمنى أن تعجبكم جميعها.
This one is called The Netherlands.
هذه تسمى هولندا.
It's by Silvarret.
مصممها سيلفاريت.
And when you start the game,
وعندما تبدأون في تشغيل اللعبة،
you have an empty piece of land.
يكون لديكم قطعة أرض فارغة.
This land, it can be based on the real world,
يمكنُ وضع هذه القطعة على أرض الواقع،
it can be hand-crafted in the map editor,
يمكن أن تُصنع يدويًا من قبل محرر الخرائط،
or you can, of course, download a city made by someone else
أو يمكنكم بالتأكيد تحميل مدينة صُنعت من قبل شخص آخر
and play in that.
واللعب فيها.
But what Silvarret has done here
ولكن الذي قام به سيلفاريت هنا
is that what he wanted to make
هو ما أراد أن يصنعه
was not a real city.
وكان تصميمًا لمدينة غير حقيقية.
This is a fantasy city,
هذه مدينة خيالية،
even though it looks real.
على الرغم من أنها تبدو حقيقية.
So what he wanted to do was a fantasy city that could be in the Netherlands.
وكان ما أراده هو بناء مدينة خيالية يمكنُ أن تكون في هولندا.
So he kind of investigated
فقام بعمل نوعٍ من التقصي حول
what are the characteristics of cities in the Netherlands
ما هي خصائص المدن في هولندا
and combined a couple of those,
والجمع بين اثنين من تلك الخصائص
and this is what he created.
وهذا ما صممه.
So it is a city,
وهذه مدينة،
but it is not a real city,
ولكنها ليست مدينة حقيقية،
but it could be.
ولكن يمكن أن تكون كذلك.
It looks just like the Netherlands.
إنها تبدو تمامًا مثل هولندا.
So the places are really densely populated.
والأماكن مكتظة بالسكان حقًا.
So what you need is highways, trains,
لذلك، فما تحتاجونه هو الطرق السريعة، والقطارات،
anything connecting these small town centers together.
وأي شيء يربط مراكز البلدة الصغيرة معًا.
Lots of people, lots of moving,
الكثير من الناس والتنقل،
so transportation is the key here.
فوسائل النقل هي الأساس هنا.
But then let's go even more on the fantasy side.
ولكن بعد ذلك لنذهب أكثر إلى الجانب الخيالي.
Let's go into the future.
هيا بنا نسافرُ إلى المستقبل.
This is one of my personal favorites.
هذه واحدة من المفضلة لديّ شخصيًا.
These city designs are what I love the most.
وأكثر شيء أحبه هو تصاميم هذه المدينة.
So this is a tiered city by Conflictnerd,
هذه المدينة المتدرجة من قبل كونفليكتنيرد،
and the basic idea is that you have concentric circle routes.
والفكرة الأساسية هي أنه لديكم طرقًا دائرية مركزية.
So the city is a big circle
فالمدينة هي دائرة كبيرة
with tinier circles inside.
بداخلها دوائر أصغر.
And the thing is that you put all of the services in the center,
والشيء المهم هو وضع جميع الخدمات في المركز،
and then people actually live on the outer ring,
ومن ثم يعيشُ الناس في المحيط الخارجي،
because there is less traffic, less noise, less pollution,
بسبب وجود حركة مرور وضوضاء وتلوث أقل.
so that is where you want to live.
فهذا هو المكان الذي تريدون العيش فيه.
But the services are still really close by.
ولكن لا تزالُ الخدمات قريبة.
They are in the center.
فهي في المركز.
And this is the soul of the game.
وهذا هو جوهر اللعبة.
The player has to understand
يجب على اللاعب أن يدرك
what are the wishes, what are the needs
ما هي رغبات، واحتياجات
of the tiny people living in the cities.
الناس صغيري الحجم الذين يعيشون في المدن.
So you need to know where you should put the things.
لذلك عليكم معرفة أين تضعون الأشياء.
Like, it's not enough to have a hospital.
على سبيل المثال، لا يكفي بأن يكون لديكم مستشفى.
It needs to be accessible.
فإنها تحتاج لأن تكون سهلة الوصول
Citizens need to reach the hospital.
يحتاج المواطنون للوصول إلى المستشفى.
And this is one way to do it.
وهناك طريقة واحدة للقيام بذلك.
So maybe this is something that we might be seeing someday.
لذلك، قد نشهدُ يومًا ما شيئًا من هذا القبيل.
And then even more into the future.
وحتى أكثر من ذلك في المستقبل.
Astergea by Yuttho.
هذه أسترجيا من قبل يوتو.
So Yuttho does YouTube videos and plays the game.
قام يوتو بعمل فيديوهات على اليوتيوب ولعب اللعبة.
What he did here was actually a 12-point series
كان ما قام به في الواقع سلسلة من 12 نقطة
of creating this city.
لبناء هذه المدينة.
So what he does is he plays the game,
وبالتالي، ما قام به هو لعب هذه اللعبة،
he records it
وسجلها،
and he explains as he's going what he's doing and why.
وهو يفسر ما الذي يقوم به، ولماذا.
And as a part of this series,
وكجزء من هذه السلسلة،
he actually did an interview with an actual urban planner
قام في الواقع بمقابلة مخطط مدني حقيقي
called Jeff Speck.
يدعى جيف سبيك
And Speck is an expert on the concept of walkability.
حيث أن سبيك خبير في مفهوم الامشائية أي تحفيز المشاة على الحركة في المكان.
The basic idea is that if you want your citizens to walk,
والفكرة الأساسية هي إذا كنتم تريدون من المواطنين أن يتحركوا
which is kind of beneficial,
لأن ذلك مفيد،
you actually need to have walking as a reasonable means of transportation.
فإنكم تحتاجون في الواقع إلى السير كوسيلة نقل معقولة.
It should be a good way to reach places.
ينبغى أن تكون وسيلة جيدة للوصول إلى الأماكن.
So what Yuttho did was that he explained this concept,
فكان ما قام به يوتو هو تفسير المفهوم،
he had Speck explain it, too,
وكان لديه سبيك لشرح ذلك أيضًا.
and then he applied it to the city that he was building.
ومن ثم طبقه على المدينة التي بناها.
So what we are seeing is Yuttho's vision of the future:
فما رأيناه هو رؤية يوتو للمستقبل،
lots of public transportation, walkways, plazas,
الكثير من وسائل النقل العام، وممرات المشاة ومراكز التسوق،
connecting high-rise buildings.
وربط المباني عالية الإرتفاع.
Maybe this is what the future might look like.
ربما هذا ما قد يبدو عليه المستقبل.
And the game system works really well for this.
ويعمل نظام اللعبة بشكل جيد جدًا لأجل ذلك.
We are seeing some real-world uses to this game.
نرى بعض استخدامات هذه اللعبة في العالم الحقيقي.
So we know that some urban planners are using it as a sketching tool,
نعلمُ أن بعض مخططي المدن يستخدمونها كأداة رسم،
so while the simulation is not completely realistic,
فى حين أن المحاكاة ليست واقعية تمامًا،
it is realistic enough that if something works in the game,
يتسمُ الأمرُ بما يكفي من الواقعية إذا كان هناك شيء يعمل في اللعبة،
it is highly likely that it will also work in the real world,
فمن المرجح جدًا أنها ستعمل في العالم الحقيقي كذلك،
so that you can actually try out things,
بحيث يمكنكم فعلًا محاولة الأشياء،
see if this intersection might fit this kind of a situation.
لمعرفة ما إذا كان يناسبُ هذا التقاطع هذا النوع من الوضع.
If we build a new road, would it help?
لو أنشأنا طريقًا جديدًا، هل سيفي بالغرض؟
And this is what you can do with this game.
وهذا ما يمكنكم فعله في هذه اللعبة.
There was one really interesting contest held
أجريت مسابقة مثيرة للاهتمام حقًا
by the Finnish city of Hämeenlinna.
من قبل مدينة هامينلينا الفلندية.
So what they did was that they had a new area
كان ما فعلوه هو أن لديهم منطقة جديدة
that they wanted to develop in the city.
أرادوا تطويرها في المدينة.
They made a map with the existing city,
صنعوا خريطة للمدينة الحالية،
they left empty the area that they would want to develop
تركوا المنطقة التي يريدون تطويرها فارغة
and shared this map.
وشاركوا هذه الخريطة.
So anyone could download the map,
وبالتالى يمكن لأي شخص تحميل الخريطة،
play the game, build the area
ولعب اللعبة وبناء المنطقة
and submit their creations to the city council.
وإرسال إبداعاتهم لمجلس المدينة.
So they have not yet built anything,
فهم لم يبنوا أي شيء بعد،
but it might just be that they use one of these plans
ولكن يمكنُ استخدام واحدة من هذه الخطط
made with the game
التي صنعت مع هذه اللعبة
to actually build the real city.
لبناء المدينة الحقيقة في الواقع.
And these videos that I have shown you,
وهذه الفيديوهات التي عرضتها عليكم،
these are the people who are coming up with new kinds of solutions.
هؤلاء الأشخاص الذين توصلوا إلى أنواع جديدة من الحلول.
We know that cities are growing.
نشهدُ أن هذه المدن آخذة بالنمو،
They're getting bigger as we go,
فهي تتسع كما نزدادُ عددًا،
and the percentage of population living in cities is projected to rise.
ومن المتوقع أن يرتفع نسبة عدد السكان الذين يعيشون في المدن.
So we need the solutions
لذلك فنحن بحاجة إلى الحلول
and these people, playing the game,
وهؤلاء الناس يلعبون اللعبة،
they are trying out different kinds of solutions.
فهم يجربون أنواعًا مختلفة من الحلول.
They might have something that is really important.
قد يكون لديهم شيء مهم حقًا.
So what we are seeing here is dream cities that might be real one day.
فما نراه هنا هو مدن الأحلام التي يمكن أن تكون حقيقة يومًا ما.
So it might be
لذلك قد يكون
that this is not just a game.
أن هذه ليست مجرد لعبة.
It might be a way
يمكن أن تكون وسيلة
to decide our own fate.
لتقريرمصيرنا.
Thank you.
شكرًا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)